<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tiger Shen</title>
    <description>Tiger Shen</description>
    <link>http://tigerthinks.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://tigerthinks.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Everything I Never Told You</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR&lt;/em&gt;: Lydia Lee, a 16 year old in Middletown, commits suicide. Her family
grapples with how this could have happened. It turns out everyone, including
Lydia, has their own internal demons that don’t come out until it’s too late.
Then they are left to figure out how they can be better in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;response&quot;&gt;Response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extremely relatable as a Chinese-American myself. Execution was just missing a
little bit of something though. Paints a vivid picture of how death, and
especially suicide, affects everyone who was close to the deceased. Shows how it
can tear people apart, but also slightly optimistically how it can help people
improve on their own flaws. Wish I could have been slightly more invested in the
characters, but don’t have a concrete suggestion for how that could have
happened – maybe not as many time jumps? Mabye a little more “show, don’t tell”
w.r.t. their emotions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next time: Ankify responses? Feelings? idk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot&quot;&gt;Plot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Takes place in 1977 in suburban Ohio&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lydia Lee is dead. At first, they think she just ran away, but she’s found in
the lake a few days after going missing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jumps back to 1955. Marilyn and James (Lydia’s parents) meet at Harvard where
she is a student at the women’s college and he is a graduate student teachinga
class. They fall in love
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Odd match. Marilyn is from Virginia and her mother is extremely
traditional, while she wants to be a doctor and is willing to endure lots of
doubt and sexism to make it happen. James is the son of Chinese immigrants
and has felt like an outcast his whole life because of this.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marilyn gets pregnant, so they get married and she drops out of school.
Marilyn’s mother disapproves, and they never see each other again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jack Wolff is introduced – a student at Lydia’s school who she spent a lot of
time with leading up to her death.. Lydia’s older brother Nath thinks he knows
something about why Lydia killed herself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stressed out, James sleeps with his teaching assistant Louisa, who is also
Chinese. He finds comfort in her familiarity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time skip back 11 years to when Lydia is 5. Marilyn’s mother dies, and going
through her mother’s old stuff and realizing how sad her life was prompts
Marilyn to want to pursue her own dreams again, which unfortunately means
leaving her family behind. She drops everything and enrolls in school&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 weeks later, she finds out she’s pregnant, so she returns home to her kids
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;During this time, Lydia vows to never disappoint her mother again, so that
her mother never leaves again. At the same time, Marilyn vows that Lydia
will be a doctor, pushing her own dreams onto her daughter&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James and Marilyn both favor Lydia, and this frustrates Nath. He gets into
Harvard though, and cannot wait to go to college.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lydia befriends Jack in the last semester before her death. Jack has a
reputation as a player, but their relationship is purely platonic and they
find that they have a lot in common. Lydia opens up to Jack about her
frustration with the pressure from her parents. Lydia is failing physics and
does not feel like she can keep up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Back in the present, after Lydia’s death, Marilyn finds out that James is
sleeping with Louisa and confronts both of them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hannah notices Lydia is distraught in the weeks leading up to her death, but
does not bring it up. All Hannah wants is to be noticed. She is used to being
the fly on the wall, ignored.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time-skip to the days before Lydia dies. Various events push her to the
breaking point, including being ignored by her older brother and jack
rejecting her sexual advances. She decides to jump into the lake even though
she cannot swim.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Back after her death, James and Marilyn make up. Nath and Hannah also come to
terms with everything. Everyone resolves to move forward with sadness, but
also to honor Lydia’s memory by not making the same mistakes again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;characters&quot;&gt;Characters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lydia Lee: girl who commits suicides and prompts the entire story. Feels
completely weighed down by the pressure from her family, wants to be her own
person but lacks the facilities to express that&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marilyn Lee: Lydia’s mom. Her whole life she has wanted to escape the “perfect
housewife” life that her mother led and wanted for her. When she finds that
she has fallen into it anyways, she decided that her daughter will be a
doctor. Puts a ton of pressure on Lydia, often doesn’t pay as much attention
to her other kids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;James Lee: Lydia’s father. Son of Chinese immigrants, and this shapes his
life. Has always felt like an outcast. Wants his son to be different, but also
feels ashamed that he is not strong enough himself. Experience of racism leads
him to become isolated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nathan Lee: Lydia’s older brother. Has always been mildly jealous of the
attention she gets, but is there for her nonetheless. Is looking forward to
being able to go to Harvard and escape his family, and that makes him neglect
his family a bit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hannah Lee: Lydia’s younger sister. Has always been extremely quiet, and feels
ignored by her family. Is very empathetic and observant of those around her.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jack Wolff: boy who lives on the same street as the Lees. Has a reputation as
a player at school. Becomes friends with Lydia in the months leading up to her
death. Is secretly gay/bisexual for Lydia’s brother Nath. When he rejects
Lydia’s sexual advances, it’s one of the things that pushes Lydia over the
edge to suicide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;themes&quot;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;racism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chinese-americanness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;appearance vs. disappearance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;secrets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;loneliness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suicide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expectations and disappointment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snippets&quot;&gt;Snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (Referring to Lydia's motivation for suicide) Because more than anything, her
  mother had wanted to stand out; because more than anything, her father had
  wanted to blend in. Because those things had been impossible. (25)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (Marilyn) She thought of her mother, the life her mother had wanted for her,
  the life her mother had hoped to lead herself: husband, children, house, her
  sole job to keep it all in order. Without meaning to, she’d acquired it. (78)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (Lydia, after her mother comes home from her disappearance) If her mother ever
  came home and told her to finish her milk, she thought, the page wavering to a
  blur, she would finish her milk. She would brush her teeth without being asked
  and stop crying when the doctor gave her shots. She would go to sleep the
  second her mother turned out the light. She would never get sick again. She
  would do everything her mother told her. Everything her mother wanted. (137)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  For her it was too late. But it wasn’t too late for Lydia. Marilyn would not
  be like her own mother, shunting her daughter toward husband and house, a life
  spent safely behind a deadbolt. She would help Lydia do everything she was
  capable of. She would spend the rest of her years guiding Lydia, sheltering
  her, the way you tended a prize rose: helping it grow, propping it with
  stakes, arching each stem toward perfection. In Marilyn’s belly, Hannah began
  to fidget and kick, but her mother could not yet feel it. She buried her nose
  in Lydia’s hair and made silent promises. Never to tell her to sit up
  straight, to find a husband, to keep a house. Never to suggest that there were
  jobs or lives or worlds not meant for her; never to let her hear doctor and
  think only man. To encourage her, for the rest of her life, to do more than
  her mother had. (146)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (James, to Nath) He did not understand why he said these things to Nath, for
  that would have meant understanding something far more painful: that Nath
  reminded him more and more of himself, of everything he wanted to forget from
  his own boyhood. (154)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (Marilyn) Everything that she had wanted for Lydia, which Lydia had never
  wanted but had embraced anyway. A dull chill creeps over her. Perhaps—and this
  thought chokes her—that had dragged Lydia underwater at last. (244)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (James) What made something precious? Losing it and finding it. All those
  times he’d pretended to lose her. (279)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/06/15/everything-i-never-told-you/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/06/15/everything-i-never-told-you/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Software Estimation: Demystifying The Black Art</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR&lt;/em&gt;: More of a reference book than a read-through book. Goes through a lot
of software estimation techniques. Meat of the book was in the first section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: taken from the “tips” appendix mainly, with context where appropriate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Estimate&lt;/strong&gt;: prediction of how long a project will take or cost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target&lt;/strong&gt;: statement of a desirable business objective&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commitment&lt;/strong&gt;: promise to deliver defined functionality at a specific level
of quality by a certain date&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimation should be treated as an unbiased, analytical process; planning
should be treated as a biased, goal-seeking process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tip 2: When you’re asked to provide an estimate, determine whether you’re
supposed to be estimating or figuring out how to hit a target.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tip 4: When you see a single-point estimate, that number’s probability
is not 100%. Ask what the probability of that number is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tip 6: Don’t intentionally underestimate. The penalty for underestimation is
more severe than the penalty for overestimation.  Address concerns about
overestimation through planning and control, not by biasing your estimates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tip 10: Many businesses value predictability more than development time, cost, or
flexibility. Be sure you understand what your business values the most.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tip 18: Include all necessary software-development activities in your estimates, not
just coding and testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tip 47: Decompose large estimates into small pieces so that you can take
advantage of the Law of Large Numbers: the errors on the high side and the
errors on the low side cancel each other out to some degree.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tough to apply just by reading all of these techniques. Major takeaway is that
everyone needs to be on the same page, and in general people underestimate the
amounts of time and resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/06/07/software-estimation-demystifying-the-black-art/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/06/07/software-estimation-demystifying-the-black-art/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Book Thief</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR&lt;/em&gt;: A German foster child named Liesel Meminger is The Book Thief. The
story of her experience during the war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;response&quot;&gt;Response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’m just numbing to all of these WWII novels but I couldn’t muster up as
much relation to these characters as the ones in The Nightingale and Beneath a
Scarlet Sky&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot&quot;&gt;Plot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death is the narrator&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liesel Meminger is going to live with a foster family, the Hubermanns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liesel’s brother dies on the trip to Molching&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;She settles into her new life with her foster father Hans (kind and gentle)
and foster mother Rosa (potty-mouth but sweet at heart). Becomes friends with
a kid named Rudy down the street&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hans teaches Liesel to read. Liesel stole one book on her way to Molching,
finds others as time goes along&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rosa does laundry for the rich people in town. As war hits, everyone is
negatively affected and she loses business&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The mayor’s wife, Frau Herrmann, is friendly to Liesel and allows her to use
the library&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Jew named Max hides in the Hubermann basement
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Max’s dad saved Hans’s life once, and Hans feels like he owes it to him to
protect him&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liesel and Max become friends. Bond over books.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The whole family has to work together to keep the secret. War rages.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nazis begin parading Jews through Molching as part of publicity efforts. Hans
tries to help one of the Jews, and gets whipped by Nazis. The house is no
longer safe, so Max must leave. Irony is that they never come check the house&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hans gets sent to war. Rudy’s dad also gets sent to war for not allowing the
Nazis to take Rudy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hans gets injured and gets sent home to recover&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liesel anxiously thinks about whether or not Max got captured. In one parade
through Molching, she sees him :(. She ends up telling Rudy about Max&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One night, while Liesel is in the basement editing her book, her
neighborhood is bombed. Hans, Rosa, Rudy, and the rest of the neighbors are
killed. When rescue workers pull Liesel out of the rubble, she finds Rudy’s
corpse and gives him the kiss he always wanted. When the workers take her away,
she leaves behind her finished book, called “The Book Thief.” Death, who has
been watching, rescues the book. Liesel goes to live with the mayor and his
wife. After the liberation of the concentration camps, Max returns to Molching
and finds Liesel. They hug and cry together. Liesel eventually grows up and
moves to Australia, where she has a family and lives to an old age. When Death
finally comes to take her soul, he shows her the book she wrote so many years
before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;characters&quot;&gt;Characters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Liesel Meminger: main character, the book thief&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Death: narrator of the story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hans Hubermann: Liesel’s foster father. They are very close. He is kindhearted
and does not agree with the Nazis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rosa Hubermann: Liesel’s foster mother. She is tough on the outside but kind
on the inside.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Max Vandenburg: Jew who hides in the Hubermannbasement for an extended time
during the war&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rudy Steiner: Liesel’s best friend. Wants to be like Jesse Owens. Loves Liesel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Frau Hermann: Mayor’s wife. Has been silent since her son died. Allows Liesel
to peruse her library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;themes&quot;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;war&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;coming-of-age&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;secrets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;literature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;duality of Nazi Germany (the good and the bad)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snippets&quot;&gt;Snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (Referring to Hans) Trust was accumulated quickly, due primarily to the brute
  strength of the man's gentleness, his _thereness_ (L484)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  Once, words had rendered Liesel useless, but now, when she sat on the floor,
  with the mayor’s wife at her husband’s desk, she felt an innate sense of
  power. It happened every time she deciphered a new word or pieced together a
  sentence. (L1908)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  Imagine smiling after a slap in the face. Then think of doing it twenty-four
  hours a day. That was the business of hiding a Jew. (L2569)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  There were the erased pages of Mein Kampf, gagging, suffocating under the
  paint as they turned. (L2757) [tiger: symbolic. bad words suffocating.]
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  Where Hans Hubermann and Erik Vandenburg were ultimately united by music, Max
  and Liesel were held together by the quiet gathering of words. (L2847)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  When the war was over and Hitler had delivered himself to my arms, Alex
  Steiner resumed work in his tailor shop. There was no money in it, but he
  busied himself there for a few hours each day, and Liesel often accompanied
  him. They spent many days together, often walking to Dachau after its
  liberation, only to be denied by the Americans. (L6282)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/06/04/the-book-thief/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/06/04/the-book-thief/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fast.ai Course Part 1: Practical Deep Learning for Coders</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most resources are on the course site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Converted notes to flashcards: https://github.com/hiromis/notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/05/19/fastai-part-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/05/19/fastai-part-1/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Dream Machine</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR&lt;/em&gt;: How the modern computer came to be, courtesy of the visionary JCR
Licklider. Incredible. None of this was an accident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prologue-tracys-dad&quot;&gt;Prologue: Tracy’s Dad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At dinner every night, Lick asks his kids: “What have you done today that was
altruistic, creative or educational?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-missouri-boys&quot;&gt;1: Missouri boys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lick was quite the character&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bringing psychology/acoustics background to computing set him apart from
others in the field
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Deep appreciation for how humans can perceive, adapt, make choices, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Studied psych at Wash U, Rochester, Swarthmore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Worked at Smitty Stevens’ psycho-acoustics at Harvard during WWII&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“No one was a stranger to him”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-the-last-transition&quot;&gt;2: The last transition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Claude Shannon writes “A Symbolic Analysis of Relay and Switching Circuits” in
1937, first use of relay circuits as logic gates which could &lt;em&gt;decide&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“A Symbolic Analysis of Relay and Switching Circuits” has just the kind of
cerebral exuberance you’d expect from a very bright twenty-one-year-old.
Shannon’s thesis is downright fun to read—and strangely compelling, given
what’s happened in the six decades since it was written.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Arguably most influential master’s thesis of the century, laying the
theoretical foundation for computer design&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Introduces the idea of &lt;em&gt;logic&lt;/em&gt; via relays and switching circuits&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At MIT&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Switching is a method to forward data packets coming in from the sender to the
receiver at the destination address. Circuit switching and packet switching
are the two most popular methods of switching. In circuit switching, data is
transferred on a dedicated channel that is to be established between the
sender and the receiver using a dedicated point-to-point connection. In packet
switching, data is split into small units called packets with each packet
being associated with a header containing signaling information about the
source and destination nodes. The packets are transmitted independently and
are processed at all intermediate nodes before reaching their destination. At
the destination, the data packets are extracted and reassembled to get the
original message.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grace Hopper finds the first bug in the summer of 1945. A moth had gotten
crushed by a relay switch in the Mark II (IBM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;von Neumann is the Einstein of mathematics: father of game theory, logic, and
more
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Crazy memory: could recite the entire opening chapter of A Tale of Two
Cities&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VN interesects with Turing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1936: Turing publishes his paper on Turing machines
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If a human mathematician can get there, a machine can get there. No matter
how clever its design, no machine can do more than Turing’s. Given enough
time and memory capacity, the lowliest handheld PC can do anything the
mightiest supercomputer on the planet can.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1943: Warren McCulloch and Walter Pitts come up with the neural network model
at University of Chicago: model the brain as a big circuit made of neurons,
each neuron receives input from other neurons, if total stimulation passes a
threshold, neuron will “fire”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VN starts sketching his architecture and is influenced by McCulloch and Pitts
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Uses their notation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Five functions: input units, output units, CPU, memory, ALU&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Von Neumann architecture is a concrete implementation of a Turing
machine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Simplest scheme possible: fetch, execute, return.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;EDVAC/ENIAC in 1947 introduce the concept of the stored program. Just treat
propgram instructions as another type of data. Separate problem-solving from
hardware
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;SOFTWARE&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-new-kinds-of-people&quot;&gt;3: New kinds of people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vannevar Bush introduces the Memex
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Memory index”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hypothetical proto-hypertext system
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Users copy and exchange trails of data&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Also hires Claude Shannon to maintain the Differential Analyzer which sparks the
following
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;This thing solves differential equations&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Claude Shannon has a fundamental theory of communication
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Information source: thing generating message (person, computer)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Transmitter: changes message into signal (voice-&amp;gt;sound wave, telephone-&amp;gt;
electric signal, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Channel: medium conducting signal (air, telephone wire, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Receiver: instrument that take signal and tries to reconstruct message (ear,
other telephone, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Destination: thing the message is intended for&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Norbert Wiener: first “skeptic” of new computer technology. Cautious optimist
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“The first indsutrial revolution, the revolution of the dark, satanic mills,
was the devaluation of the human arm by the comptetition of machinery. The
moderd industrial revolution is similarly bound to devalue the human brain,
at least in its simpler and more routine decisions.”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Vision of information age: it tied together communication, computation, and
control&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is “cybernetics”: study of control and communication in the animal and
machine&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-the-freedom-to-make-mistakes&quot;&gt;4: The freedom to make mistakes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1950: MIT physicist George Valley committee to upgrade Pentagon air defense
strategy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Two recommendations: sub-contract to a technical organization. Use digital
computers to cordinate surveillance, target tracking&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Project Lincoln’s goal of understanding how machines and humans could work
together as a system was just an extension of Lick’s own inner quest:
understanding how the human brain itself worked as a system.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Got the best psychology students in the country&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Indeed, Lick was already honing the leadership style that he would use to such
effect a decade later with the nationwide computer community. Call it rigorous
laissez-faire. On the one hand, like his mentor Smitty Stevens, Lick expected
his students to work very, very hard; he had nothing but contempt for laziness
and no time to waste on sloppy work or sloppy thinking. Moreover, he insisted
that his students master the tools of their craft, whether they be experimental
technique or mathematical analysis. On the other hand, Lick almost never told
his students what to do in the lab, figuring that it was far better to let them
make their own mistakes and find their own way. And imagination, of course, was
always welcome; the point here was to have fun.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lincoln Lab + IBM collaborate on SAGE, the Semi-Automated Ground Environment,
in 1954
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Enormous impact on the history of computing
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Brought brightest computer minds to MIT&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Billions of $$$ of Pentagon money helped IBM become the biggest computer
manufacturer in the world&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Brought real-time computing to the business world&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Planted the seed of the idea that computers and humans could work together
and be more effective than working separately&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turing writes “Computing Machinery and Intelligence” in 1950
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thinking machines: what does it mean to be a machine, and what does it mean
to think?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Turing test: if a computer is indistinguishable from a human via chat
interface, it is thinking&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Accused of being gay, put on estrogen treatment, commits suicide in 1954&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;von Neumann gets bone cancer and dies in 1957 :/
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Surrounded by 4 members of the cabinet and all military chiefs of staff at
time of death because he was so important to the country’s nuclear weapons
program&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;George Miller is a psychologist who worked with Lick
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Disagreement with the behaviorist movement. Behaviorists say that any
internal states are inaccessible to outside observers, so the only way for
organisms to be understood is by cataloging observable inputs and outputs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Miller focuses on cognitive processes. Starts the field of cognitive
psychology with Noam Chomsky, and this replaces behaviorism. Invented the
term “chunk” to apply to units of things you can remember&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chomsky attacks behaviorism using language: how can you avoid talking about
mental states when the whole point of language is to communicate things like
ideas, images, feelings?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Language has almost infinite combinations of expression&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There is a structure to sentences, which behaviorists cannot account for&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The pinnacle of all possible mathematical machines – the Turing machine –
is also the baseline, the minimum for human cognition. This is part of a
hierarchy&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allen Newell and Herbert Simon work on the Logic Theorist in 1955
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Solve mathematical proofs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Have to use heuristics because there is a combinatorial explosion of
possibilities
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The unique power of heuristic reasoning lies in its ability to cope with
the complex and the unexpected, to make acceptable choices when there
isn’t enough time to make the ideal choice, to hunker down and keep on
going when a precisely defined algorithm would be overwhelmed by the
combinatorial explosion. In effect, heuristic reasoning is what allows us
to go through life in a chronic state of controlled panic.&lt;/em&gt; (L3380)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trace the progression of ideas:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;mid-40’s: after cybernetics, we understand that a computer can have memory
through the mechanism of feedback&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;After McCulloch and Pitts, we can understand that the brain uses neuron
activations to process information&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;After Chomsky and Newell and Simon and Miller, we know that reasoning can
come from information processing through heuristics. This is the birth of
cognitive science
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“Logic Theorist was a demonstration that you could have artifacts that
would behave intelligently. Even if you didn’t believe the further
assumption that the way the computer did it was the same way we do it,
this in itself was enough to free the psychological imagination. If you
talk about the computer’s having a memory, then certainly the
behavioristic ban on concepts like memory was no longer necessary. And if
a computer could be prepared to anticipate any one of n alternatives, then
certainly the ban on expectations was no longer valid.” - Miller&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wesley Clark working on a computer called the TX-2 at MIT in 1957. Invites
Lick to check it out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-the-tale-of-the-fig-tree-and-the-wasp&quot;&gt;5: The tale of the fig tree and the wasp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TX-2 group realizes in 1955 that if computers are going to ever go mainstream,
must replace vacuum tubes with transistors. Smaller, faster, cheaper. Vacuum
tubes are too large and gave off a ton of heat and were unreliable
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Transistors were new&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clark sketches TX-0&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ken Olsen raises money to take transistor computers mainstream and starts
Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working with the TX-2 sparks idea for Lick
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;So, Lick wondered, what would happen if you put humans and computers
together as a system? What would happen if you let the machines take over
all those dreary, algorithmic chores they were so good at? How much of your
time would be opened up for real creativity?
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Empirically, he spent 85% of his “creative” time on clerical work
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Could this be turned into some sort of symbiosis?&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1956 Lick is persuaded to join a firm called BBN (Bolt Beranek and Newman)
as the director of psychoacoustics and engineering lab
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;He is given a lot of autonomy and set about building a dream team&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Lick collected people,” says his former student Tom Marill, who was struck
by the way his mentor always tried to bring his favorites along as he moved
from place to place. “He was very bright, he was very articulate, and
because of that he was able to get very good people. They liked being
collected.”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;He buys a new IBM card machine to learn how to program&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The IBM computer is woefully insufficient. Around the same time, DEC releases
their first computer
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s the PDP-1 (Programmed Data Processor) and BBN got the first one&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Finally a serious cmoputer. 2x the price, 1000x the performance of the IBM
LGP-30
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“There had never before been a machine that was this much in front of the
competition. And never since. It was a singular event.” (Ed Fredkin)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lick uses this computer to write educational software for his children&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;John McCarthy joined BBN
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Never impressed by much :)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Invented the field of AI
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;1956 6-week conference: “Dartmouth Summer Research Project on Artificial
Intelligence”&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Thought the Logic Theorist was sloppy. Wanted to build an Advice Taker
that draws from a database of propositions etc.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Invented Lisp, interactive symbol-processing programming language
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Static resource allocation wouldn’t work for AI because it is so dynamic&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Lisp = List Processor
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Functional programming. Most powerful and compelling feature&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Introduced the idea of an interpreter&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Allowed for composition of complex programs&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Invented time-sharing
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Idea “just popped in his head”. Seemed obvious to him.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lick writes a paper called “Man-Computer Symbiosis” in 1960
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incredible paper. Laid out the entire vision for US computer research&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“The fig tree is pollinated only by the insect Blastophaga grossorum [the
fig wasp]. The larva of the insect lives in the ovary of the fig tree, and
there it gets its food. The tree and the insect are thus heavily
interdependent: the tree cannot reproduce without the insect; the insect
cannot eat without the tree; together, they constitute not only a viable
but a productive and thriving partnership. This cooperative ‘living
together in intimate association, or even close union, of two dissimilar
organisms’ is called symbiosis. … The purposes of this paper are to
present the concept [of] and, hopefully, to foster the development of
man-computer symbioses.”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A relationship like having a colleague who can help you think when problems
get hard&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Knew way too much about the brain to be an optimist about AI. Pretty
ambivalent.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Viewed programming as a profound activity. Solving programming problems can
hint at the nature of intellectual processes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Loved the idea of a model: “any convenient simulation of reality”
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ok so let’s dive into MODELS&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Ordinary mathematical models are static models. They are representations in
symbols, usually written in pencil or ink on paper. They do not behave in
any way. They do not ‘solve themselves.’ For any transformation to be made,
for any solution to be achieved, information contained in the model must be
read out of the static form and processed in some active processor, such as
a mathematician’s brain or a computing machine. A dynamic model, on the
other hand, exists in its static form only while it is inactive. The dynamic
model can be set into action, by one means or another, and when it is
active, it does exhibit behavior and does ‘solve itself.’” The Curtiss Robin
was a dynamic model in this sense, he explained: once the fan was turned on,
it flew. It was active. The same was true of the analog electronic
simulations he had once experimented with at the MIT acoustics lab.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In richness, plasticity, facility, and economy, the mental model has no
peer.” Included among those mental models are images recalled from memory,
expectations about the probable course of events, fantasies of what might
be, perceptions of other people’s motives, unspoken assumptions about human
nature, hopes, dreams, fears, paradigms—essentially all conscious thought.
Of course, Lick and Taylor would continue, “[the mental model] has
shortcomings. It will not stand still for careful study. It cannot be made
to repeat a run. No one knows just how it works. It serves its owner’s hopes
more faithfully than it serves reason. It has access only to the information
stored in one man’s head. It can be observed and manipulated only by one
person.” But if you could join mental models to computer models, Lick
reasoned, and if you could get the two of them into just the right kind of
symbiotic relationship, then you could overcome every one of those
limitations.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Addresses complexity limitation by being able to handle huge amounts of
data and represent knowledge as programs&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Addresses the limitation of confinement of knowledge to a single head by
allowing data to be displayed on many screens and viewed by many people&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;In addition, Lick wrote, this computerized system system would be of
enormous help in meeting the challenge of “ordered information”: finding
and applying the relevant research results, utilizing the expertise of
outside consultants, coordinating the efforts of design engineers,
analyzing a flood of test data, scheduling routine maintenance, planning
for continual evolution and growth—and on and on.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the beginning of the 1960s, then, a decade and a half before the
microcomputer revolution began in the garages of Silicon Valley, and a full
thirty years before the dawn of the Internet Age, the air around Cambridge was
already alive with the essential ideas:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;graphics-rich personal workstations and the notion of human-computer symbiosis&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;time-sharing and the notion of computer-aided collaborative work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;networks and the notion of an on-line community&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on-line libraries and the notion of instant, universal access to knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;computer languages and the notion of a new, digital medium of expression.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MIT Model Railroad Club become the first “hackers” in Spring 1959 after
participating in McCarthy’s first-ever programming class
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“hack” comes from MIT slang for a practical joke&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wrote little software like number converters, audio playing, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-the-phenomena-surrounding-computers&quot;&gt;6: The phenomena surrounding computers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eisenhower consolidates all space research under ARPA in 1957 (Advanced
Research Projects Agency)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In 1962 Lick becomes director, one year leave of absence from BBN. Came with
System Development Corporation contract ($6M), so his budget was $10M. Moves to
Washington&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Didn’t like the SDC batch processing approach, needed them to buy into time
sharing
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brought MIT folks to Santa Monica in November and convinced them time
sharing was better&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Starts assembling the TEAM
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Traveled around everywhere trying to get talent together from universities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wanted proposals for computer research. Carnegie, RAND, Stanford, Berkeley&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;One proposal that ended up on his desk was from Douglas Engelbart
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;FLASH-1: The difficulty of mankind’s problems was increasing at a greater
rate than our ability to cope. (We are in trouble.)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;FLASH-2: Boosting mankind’s ability to deal with complex, urgent problems
would be an attractive candidate as an arena in which a young person might
try to “make the most difference.” (Yes, but there’s that question of what
does the young electrical engineer do about it? Retread for a role as
educator, research psychologist, legislator… ? Is there any handle there
that an electrical engineer could … ?)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;FLASH-3: Aha—graphic vision surges forth of me sitting at a large CRT
console, working in ways that are rapidly evolving in front of my eyes
(beginning from memories of the radar-screen consoles I used to service).&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Within a few days, he said, the imagery of FLASH-3 had evolved into a vision
of a general-purpose, computer-powered information environment. It would
include documents mixing text and graphics on the same CRT display. It would
include whole new systems of symbols and methodologies to help users do
their heavy thinking. And it would include network-assisted collaborations
to allow people to work together in ways that would be more effective than
anything anyone had ever seen before. Within a few weeks he had committed
his career to this vision, which he now called “augmenting the human
intellect.”&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Spoke about phases of human evolution:
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Concept manipulation: non-verbal mental concepts&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Symbol manipulation: words and numbers&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Manual external symbol manipulation: graphic representations of concepts&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;Computers introduce &lt;em&gt;automated external symbol manipulation&lt;/em&gt;: computers
can run programs on their own&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bob Fano, Minsky, and McCarthy need a proposal to get money from ARPA to MIT. They
come up with Project MAC for Multiple-Access Computer
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This was a time-shared information utility&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Needed to do it in 6 months. And without any ARPA funding yet
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Corbato, Dennis, Greenberger, Minsky, Ross, Selfridgbe, Teager&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Galactic network in April 1963
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lick dictated to his Principal Investigators (Fano, McCarthy, Uncapher,
Engelbart, Feigenbaum, Perlis) that they would have to join up with Arpanet
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;In short, he said, the various ARPA-funded sites would have to take all
their time-sharing computers, once they became operational, and link them
into a national system. “If such a network as I envisage nebulously could
be brought into operation,” Lick wrote, “we would have at least four large
computers, perhaps six or eight small computers, and a great assortment of
disc files and magnetic tape units—not to mention the remote consoles and
Teletype stations—all churning away.”&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MIT time-sharing becomes a huge success because people begin sharing programs
with each other
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tom Van Vleck writes the MAIL command&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Now, however, time-sharing had made exchanging software trivial: you just
stored one copy in the public repository and thereby effectively gave it to
the world. “Immediately,” says Fano, “people began to document their
programs and to think of them as being usable by others. They started to
build on each other’s work.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lick decides to stay at ARPA
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;with rare exceptions—notably that first encounter with SDC—Lick was much
more interested in being a mentor than in being a micromanager. As long as
people made reasonable progress in the right direction, he would let them
find their own way.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Things keep humming. He funds Newell, Simon, Perlis at Carnegie&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mouse invented at Stanford Research Institute
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;They were working on interactive computing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Needed a screen selection device&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Finally, as they were all sitting around brainstorming one day, Engelbart
came up with the idea of a little gadget that the user could roll around on
the desktop with one hand while the cursor tracked its motion on the screen.
Since it didn’t seem any sillier than some of the other things they had
tried, Bill English went off to the SRI machine shop and made one. It was
essentially just a block of wood about the size of a pack of cigarettes,
with some rollers set into the bottom and a wire coming out the front end to
communicate the motion of the rollers to the computer. Engelbart wasn’t
totally satisfied with this contraption, either. And yet when the NLS team
hooked up all the selection devices to their computer and gave users a
choice, they discovered that people were consistently choosing the little
gadget. The preference was so strong, in fact, that they eventually
abandoned everything else; the gadget had become their standard. And by that
time, of course—though no one on the SRI team can now remember when, or how,
or why it started—they had all taken to calling the thing a mouse. It was
more of a joke than a name, really. They would surely find a more dignified
term in time. But until then, well, it just seemed to fit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around here, Lick sends out Intergalactic Network memo. This was the precursor
to Arpanet, which was the precursor to the internet.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In short, he said, the various ARPA-funded sites would have to take all
their time-sharing computers, once they became operational, and link them
into a national system. “If such a network as I envisage nebulously could be
brought into operation,” Lick wrote, “we would have at least four large
computers, perhaps six or eight small computers, and a great assortment of
disc files and magnetic tape units—not to mention the remote consoles and
Teletype stations—all churning away.” Lick went on to discuss many examples
of how people might use such a system, as well as the technical challenges
of bringing it into being. At one point he even described something
strikingly similar to the migratory Java applets that would appear at the
turn of the millennium: “With a sophisticated network-control system, I
would not [have to] decide whether to send the data and have them worked on
by programs somewhere else, or bring in programs and have them work on my
data.” The computer could make such decisions automatically, he said—meaning
that software could float free of individual machines. Programs and data
would actually live on the net. And so it went for seven pages, in what was
arguably the most significant document that Lick would ever write. It’s true
that his proposal was just an elaboration on the network of “thinking
centers” he had envisioned in his 1960 “Symbiosis” paper—enriched, perhaps,
by the more recent speculations around MIT about citywide information
utilities. But in just a few years, this memorandum to the Intergalactic
Network would become the direct inspiration for the Arpanet, which would
eventually evolve into today’s Internet.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile, things humming along at Project MAC
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Working on an operating system called Multics
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Could run without interruption, multi-processor&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;In the meantime, System/360 by IBM is a batch-processing disaster
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;So IBM commissions a time-sharing approach. They hire Lick&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“When you look at Lick’s legacy, two very distinct things stand out,” says Bob
Fano. “One is that he was a very imaginative, creative psychoacoustics man.
Second, says Fano, when Lick was presented with a miraculous,
never-to-be-repeated opportunity to turn his vision into reality, he had the
guts to go for it, and the skills to make it work.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lick: It was more than just a collection of bright people. It was a thing
that organized itself into a community, so that there was some competition
and some cooperation, and it resulted in the emergence of a field.”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-the-intergalactic-network&quot;&gt;7: The intergalactic network&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bob Taylor is Lick’s biggest fan. Works for NASA. Helps Lick a lot when Lick
is at ARPA&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1965, Taylor proposes linking all 16 IPTO contractors together in one
network
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Timing is right because they are just starting to become operational&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Obviously some pushback&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Taylor was willing to let Roberts and the rest of the world believe anything
they wanted—so long as the network got built.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ARPA would make a series of massive long-distance calls and just never hang
up. More precisely, the agency would go to AT&amp;amp;T and lease a series of
high-capacity phone lines linking one ARPA site to the next. A diagram of the
resulting network would thus look something like a road map of the interstate
highway system,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The farther a message traveled, the greater the chances that one or more bits
would be garbled by static and distortion on the line. And in the digital
world, one erroneous bit might easily spell disaster. Thus the digital
postcards, or “packets,” in modern parlance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So in sum, said Roberts, that was the plan: full-time access, messages divided
into packets, and distributed control. Now, who wanted to help?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to route stuff?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wes Clark: routing computers are responsible for moving stuff
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;IMPs: Interface Messaging Processors&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Simplify life for everybody. ARPA could take responsibility for designing
and implementing the network proper—meaning the information highways and
the digital interchanges—without having to worry that some contractor
somewhere would mess up his site’s programming and thereby bollix up the
whole system. And the contractors, for their part, could focus on one
comparatively simple task—establishing a link from their central computer
to the routing computer—without having to worry about all the ins and outs
of all the other computers on the network.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first RFC comes from SRI/Utah/UCLA/Santa Barbara meetings in ‘69. They were the
first 4 members of Arpanet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Around same time (1968) Engelbart gives the first demo of interactive
computing at the Fall Joint Computer Conference in SF&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BBN wins the right to build Arpanet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;J. C. R. Licklider again and again took jobs that required him to be an
administrator—and then was almost contemptuous of the skills it took to do
those jobs right.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Made Project MAC almost go off the rails&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multics comes out in 1970
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Witness the fact that the Association for Computing Machinery would award
Corbató its 1991 Turing Award, computerdom’s most prestigious honor. For all
its complexity and delay, Multics gave living proof that a grown-up
operating system was possible—that sophisticated memory management, a
hierarchical file system, careful attention to security, and all the rest
could be integrated into a single, coherent whole. In that sense, Multics
was a prototype for virtually all the operating systems to follow.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie launch Unix in mid-1970s from Bell Labs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1972 Arpanet is released to the world at large at ICCC, International
Conference on Computers and Communications, in Washington&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A BBN engineer named Ray Tomlinson adds email as an add-on to Arpanet and it
takes off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are tons of ways Arpanet could have failed, but it didn’t
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ARPA directorship style: progress, not progress reports&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Larry Roberts starts the Network Working Group
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Most democractic forum!!&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;These young researchers who built hardware, debugged software, got hands
dirty, made the whole thing happen&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People start leaving ARPA for Xerox PARC (Palo Alto Research Center)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;They join Bob Taylor there&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-living-in-the-future&quot;&gt;8: Living in the future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;George Pake hires Taylor to run the lab&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taylor’s motto was “Never hire ‘good’ people, because ten good people together
can’t do what a single great one can do.”
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Taylor is very good at getting … a collection of extremely intelligent
and opinionated egomaniacs to work together reasonably well without fighting
each other,” he noted. “Damned if I know how! I can’t do it, but he does.”2&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;All of the various gadgets had to be part of that system. And to achieve
that goal, Taylor knew, he somehow had to get all these maverick geniuses
moving in the same direction, without forcing everyone to move in lockstep.
Somehow he had to give them a sense of purpose and group cohesion, without
crushing spontaneity and individual initiative. Somehow, in short, he had to
set things up so they would freely follow their own instincts—and end up
organizing themselves. This is arguably the fundamental dilemma of modern
management, not to mention the fundamental political challenge in any
democracy; leaders have been grappling with it for centuries.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;And when the arguments got heated, which they often did, the minister’s son
would do his best to convert a “class-one” disagreement—one in which the
combatants were simply yelling at each other—into a “class two”
disagreement, in which each side could explain the other side’s position to
the other side’s satisfaction. You don’t have to believe the other guy, he
would tell them. You just have to give a fair account of what he’s saying.
And it worked.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;LOVE THIS!!&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bill English. Alan Kay
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Kay was a very insubordinate person&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Had the idea to include procedure for unpackaging data &lt;em&gt;with the data
itself&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Object-oriented programming!! From a system called Simula where everything
was described in nouns and verbs
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;“For the first time,” he recalled, “I thought of the whole as the entire
computer and wondered why anyone would want to divide it up into weaker
things called data structures and procedures. Why not divide it up into
little computers, as time-sharing was starting to? But not in dozens. Why
not thousands of them, each simulating a useful structure?”&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kay: Dynabook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cerf and Kahn: TCP/IP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;9-licks-kids&quot;&gt;9: Lick’s kids&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Back in his natural habitat of Tech Square, meanwhile, he had reverted to
being Lick at his best: not functioning as a manager and paper pusher, a role
in which he was a disaster, but serving as visionary, teacher, mentor, and
friend. Around the late 70’s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the mid 70’s, the “whitecoats” start to get overrun by the hobbyists
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Hardware: could buy cheap, less-powerful computers and run them all the time
(PDP-8, PDP-11, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Software: Unix!! Built with hacking in mind
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;A response to the complexity of Multics&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Sweet, quick, and clean&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Then they released C as well, and all of a sudden, tons of people could
program&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then began the Usenet migration
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Started having user groups&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“Life will be happier for the on-line individual because the people with
whom one interacts most strongly will be selected more by commonality of
interests and goals than by accidents of proximity.” - Taylor and Licklider,
1968&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They were the spiritual brothers of the MIT hackers and the freewheeling Unix
mavens. They were the people who had been ham-radio operators and/or stereo
buffs since they were teenagers, often using equipment they had built
themselves from mail-order kits, or from scratch. They were the guys who had
gotten intrigued by the minicomputers they’d encountered at work or at school.
And for no “logical” reason whatsoever—certainly none that they could explain
to their spouses—they were the people who wanted computers of their own at
home, to play with, to experiment with, to experience. Enter the Altair.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Altair was the first commercially successful microcomputer
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Received over 10k orders, expecting only a few hundred&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Bill Gates and Paul Allen write Altair BASIC&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Eventually the founder, H. Edward Roberts, sold out to a big hardware
company because he was so exasperated with the “soap opera”. He became a
doctor&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apple Computer Company was next in line
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Founded by Homebrew Computer Club members&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Apple II had a ton of commercial success&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;On the software side, Microsoft releases MS-DOS operating system&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Microcomputer revolution goes huge into the 80s&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So there it was: the “personal” part of the personal-distributed-computing
paradigm was diffusing outward in the form of workstations, while the
“distributed” part was doing the same in the form of Ethernet.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ethernet standard is an agreement licensed to Intel and Xerox. Initially
proposed by Gordon Bell at DEC&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That left the Smalltalk graphical user interface, together with all the other
Alto software—the embodiment of computing as a medium of expression and
exploration. But this idea was making its way into the world, too, thanks to a
fateful show-and-tell at the very end of the 1970s.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Steve Jobs’s visit to PARC has become something of a mythology
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;When Jobs and his top engineers finally showed up for an afternoon visit
in December 1979, the presentation was as minimal as Goldberg could make
it. She and her Smalltalk colleagues gave Jobs and company the standard
visitor’s tour: the Alto, the mouse, Bravo word processing, some drawing
programs—nothing that the whole world hadn’t seen before. And afterward
their guests departed, apparently satisfied. Two days later, having
realized almost at once that they’d been shortchanged, Jobs and his crew
showed up in the PARC lobby with no advance warning. They wanted to see
the good stuff, they said—now. There ensued several hours of argument
between the Smalltalk team and its bosses. But in the end, after a direct
order, with Xerox headquarters’ backing up XDC, a red-faced Goldberg did
indeed show Jobs and his people the good stuff. This included education
applications written by Goldberg herself, programming tools created by
Larry Tesler, and animation tools cooked up by Diana Merry for combining
pictures and text in a single document—all of it increasingly irksome.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And that was the essential tragedy, he says: whereas headquarters understood
marketing but not computers, the wizards out on Coyote Hill Road understood
computers but not marketing. They had gone into the design process believing
fervently in the PARC vision, in personal distributed computing as a whole,
integrated system. They knew that it far transcended anything else on the
market. And they couldn’t imagine that customers would want anything less.
They’d also been given to understand that cost was no constraint: their target
was the corporate world, the Fortune 500—scale customers that were used to
shelling out hundreds of thousands of dollars for computer equipment. The
result was an unfettered exuberance that led the Star’s designers into at
least three critical errors. The first and most obvious was a rampant case of
feature-itis: they loaded up the Star software with every neat thing they
could think of, until it had grown to roughly a million lines of code and was
at the ragged edge of what the 1981-vintage hardware could support. Indeed,
that was the first thing users noticed: the Star was painfully, maddeningly
sloooow.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Also: made it a closed system
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;All software and hardware had to come from Xerox&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Had to guess what customers wanted instead of tapping into wider
community. No spreadsheet program on the STAR. Nobody at PARC ever thought
to write one because nobody in a research lab ever needed one. Inverse of
priorities of the business world&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;No inexpensive, low-risk entry path for customers. Minimal installation
cost $100,000. Apple II was $1500&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Passed up tons of chances to make something simpler&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Back in the 1970s, it seems, computer users in corporate America had been
facing much the same frustration faced by researchers such as Steve Wolff: the
“whitecoats,” or management information service (MIS) departments, dictated
the terms. Big companies relied on mainframes, a few minis here and there,
and, for “desktop” applications, lots of dedicated word-processing machines
from vendors such as Wang and IBM. You played by the MIS rules or not at all.
Ah, but then the micros came along, the high-tech embodiment of individual
autonomy, hands-on control, and freedom—not to mention the source of a
spreadsheet application, VisiCalc, that you couldn’t get any other way.
Naturally, the MIS types tried to outlaw the things. But it was hopeless; the
micros were cheap enough that a manager with any imagination could easily hide
them in the petty-cash budget. Within a very few years, the steady trickle of
surreptitious Apple IIs had become a flood of IBM PCs, PC clones, and Macs,
and the MIS departments had effectively given up. In fairness, they did have a
legitimate gripe. With the flood of micros had come a flood of new software,
some of it very good—WordPerfect, dBase, and Lotus 1–2–3, for example—but much
of it flaky and bug-ridden, and all of it incompatible with most companies
existing applications. Too often, the resulting chaos wasted more of a
company’s time than it saved. But there was no way to keep personal computers
out of the office, especially not when more and more employees were using them
at home. So instead the MIS managers bowed to the inevitable and started
linking the various PCs together into local-area networks, which let them at
least get some of the data moved onto a central server where they could be
shared. 3Com had helped jump-start the process in 1982 by being among the
first to offer an Ethernet card for the new IBM PC. And the company had
prospered accordingly throughout the 1980s and 1990s, as the office norm
increasingly came to resemble what Bob Taylor and his crew had first imagined
two decades earlier: individual computers, Ethernet networking, digital
printing, WYSIWYG text editing and graphics programs, a windowing
interface—personal distributed computing in full.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 1983, physicist and integrated circuit specialist William J. Spencer became
director of PARC. Spencer and Taylor disagreed about budget allocations for
CSL (exemplified by the ongoing institutional divide between computer science
and physics) and CSL’s frustration with Xerox’s inability to recognize and use
what they had developed. By the end of the year, Taylor and most of the
researchers at CSL left Xerox. A coterie of leading computer scientists
(including Licklider, Donald Knuth and Dana Scott) expressed their displeasure
with Xerox’s decision not to retain Taylor in a letter-writing campaign to CEO
David Kearns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In retrospect, of course, Berners-Lee’s combination of hypertext and browsing
would prove to be one of those brilliantly simple ideas that change
everything. By giving users something to see, it set off a subtle but powerful
shift in the psychology of the Internet. No longer would it be just an
abstract communication channel, like the telephone or the TV; instead, it
would become a place, an almost tangible reality that you could enter into,
explore, and even share with the other people you found there. It would become
the agora, the electronic commons, the information infrastructure, cyberspace.
Because of Berners-Lee’s hypertext browsing, users would finally begin to get
it about the Internet. And they would want more. …
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;1990: Release of the World Wide Web. Following trend of streamlining
networks etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An integrated, open, universally accessible Multinet wouldn’t just happen on
its own, he pointed out. It would require cooperation and effort on a time
scale of decades, “a long, hard process of deliberate study, experiment,
analysis, and development.” That process, in turn, could be sustained only by
the forging of a collective vision, some rough consensus on the part of
thousands or maybe even millions of people that an open electronic commons was
worth having. And that, wrote Lick, would require leadership. Good luck. The
pessimistic scenario, in contrast, would require nothing more than laissez
faire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technology isn’t destiny, no matter how inexorable its evolution may seem; the
way its capabilities are used is as much a matter of cultural choice and
historical accident as politics is, or fashion. And in the early 1960s history
still seemed to be on the side of batch processing, centralization, and
regimentation.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Licklider’s generous funding to paradigms like time-sharing, packet
switching, TCP/IP, led to technology as we know it today&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/05/07/the-dream-machine/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/05/07/the-dream-machine/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Breakfast of Champions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR&lt;/em&gt;: My first Vonnegut book. Definitely a ride. Not sure I ‘got’ everything
I was supposed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot&quot;&gt;Plot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Kurt Vonnegut’s  most beloved characters, the aging writer Kilgore Trout,
finds to his horror that a Midwest car dealer named Dwayne Hoover is taking his
fiction as truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trout is invited to speak at a festival in Midland City, where Dwayne lives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dwayne is becoming more and more mentally unstable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dwayne reads a novel of Trout’s that explains to Dwayne that he is the only
thing in the universe with true free will&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dwayne becomes unhinged and beats up a ton of people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vonnegut inserts himself into the book and talks to Trout, telling Trout that
he (Vonnegut) is the Creator of the Universe. Trout takes this in stride.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written in short snippets, separated by three dots. Uses simple language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;characters&quot;&gt;Characters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kilgore Trout: sci-fi writer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dwayne Hoover: Midwest car dealer. Slowly going crazy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eliot Rosewater: rich man who sponsors Trout to speak at the Midland City Arts
Festival&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harry LeSabre: secret transvestite, self-conscious about it, works for Hoover&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;themes&quot;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;war&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;racism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;success&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;politics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pollution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suicide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snippets&quot;&gt;Snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  Here was the core of the bad ideas which Trout gave Dwayne: Everybody on Earth
  was a robot, with one exception--Dwayne Hoover. (14)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  As I approached my fiftieth birthday, I had become more and more enraged and
  mystified by the idiot decisions made by my countrymen. And then I had come
  suddenly to pity them, for I understood how innocent and natural it was for
  them to behave so abominably, and with such abominable results: They were
  doing their best to live like people invented in story books. This was the
  reason Americans shot each other so often: It was a convenient literary device
  for ending short stories and books.
  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;
  Why were so many Americans treated by their government as though their lives
  were as disposable as paper facial tissues? Because that was the way authors
  customarily treated bit-part players in their made-up tales.
  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;
  And so on.
  &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;
  Once I understood what was making America such a dangerous, unhappy nation of
  people who had nothing to do with real life, I resolved to shun storytelling.
  I would write about life. Every personw ould be exactly as important as any
  other. All facts would also be given equal weightiness. Nothing would be left
  out. Let others bring order to chaos. I would bring chaos to order, instead,
  which I think I have done. (215)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/05/06/breakfast-of-champions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/05/06/breakfast-of-champions/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beneath a Scarlet Sky</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR&lt;/em&gt;: “Pino Lella’s story as a young Italian man during World War 2. Slightly
worse than The Nightingale but great story nonetheless. Starting to warm up to
war story genre. Strong characters.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plot&quot;&gt;Plot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pino Lella wants nothing to do with the war or the Nazis. He’s a normal Italian
teenager—obsessed with music, food, and girls—but his days of innocence are
numbered. When his family home in Milan is destroyed by Allied bombs, Pino joins
an underground railroad helping Jews escape over the Alps, and falls for Anna, a
beautiful widow six years his senior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to protect him, Pino’s parents force him to enlist as a German
soldier—a move they think will keep him out of combat. But after Pino is
injured, he is recruited at the tender age of eighteen to become the personal
driver for Adolf Hitler’s left hand in Italy, General Hans Leyers, one of the
Third Reich’s most mysterious and powerful commanders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with the opportunity to spy for the Allies inside the German High Command,
Pino endures the horrors of the war and the Nazi occupation by fighting in
secret, his courage bolstered by his love for Anna and for the life he dreams
they will one day share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leyers eventually ends up saving Jews&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the Italians win, they shoot Anna for being a traitor since she was the
maid of Dolly, Leyers’s mistress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;characters&quot;&gt;Characters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pino: main character, teenager&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mimo: Pino’s brother, fights directly for the resistance. Resents Pino
initially, thinks of Pino as a traitor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hans Leyers: Nazi general who Pino drives around after Pino is able to fix his
car&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anna: beautiful widow who Pino sees before the war starts in earnest and falls
in love with. Maid to Leyers’ mistress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Father Re: Catholic priest who organizes getting Jews across the border to
Switzerland&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michele: Pino’s dad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Albert: Pino’s uncle, involved with resistance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;themes&quot;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;war&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;coming-of-age&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;secrets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;romance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snippets&quot;&gt;Snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  &quot;Decimation functions psychologically,&quot; Leyers explained. &quot;It's designed to
  quell the threat of revolt through abject fear. But historically, using
  brutality against civilians in reprisal breeds more hatred than obedience.&quot;
  (235)
  [Tiger: Leyers showing his human side]
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  &quot;Anna kissed him a fourth time. Pino thought he heard a woodwind join the
  strings vibrating in his chest, and his mind and body were reduced to one
  thing, to the music of Anna-Marta and nothing more.&quot; (250)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  &quot;How do you find happiness?&quot; [Pino]
  Anna paused, then said, &quot;You start by looking right around you for the
  blessings you have. When you find them, be grateful.&quot; (260)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/04/09/beneath-a-scarlet-sky/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/04/09/beneath-a-scarlet-sky/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ruth</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Naomi loses her husband and two sons. Ruth, one of her daughters-in-law, stays
with her, and they return to Bethelehem together. Two widows have very little
social capital in Israel, but one of Naomi’s husband’s relatives, Boaz, shows
them kindness and allows Ruth to pick through the fields after his men have
gone through them. Ruth eventually marries Boaz.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snippets&quot;&gt;Snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  Ruth said, &quot;Do not press me to leave you or to turn back from following you!
  Where you go, I will go; Where you lodge, I will lodge; your people shall be
  my people, and your God my God. Where you die, I will die—there will I be
  buried. May the Lord do thus and so to me, and more as well, if even death
  parts me from you!&quot; When Naomi saw that she was determined to go with her, she
  said no more to her. (NRSV 1:16-18) [Tiger: LOYALTY]
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/03/31/ruth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/03/31/ruth/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wonder</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TL;DR&lt;/em&gt;: Story of a kid named August who has a disfigured face who goes to
school for the first time. It’s definitely a kid’s book. I appreciated the
message a lot and it was well-told, but I think I would have enjoyed it much
more 10 years ago :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Switches perspectives between kids throughout book&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;August: “I won’t describe what I look like. Whatever you’re thinking, it’s
probably worse.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Friends:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Jack Will is poor but wants to fit in&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Julian is the “popular kid”&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vivian is the sister&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Justin is Vivian’s new boyfriend&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Miranda is Vivian’s old friend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;snippets&quot;&gt;Snippets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  Mr. Browne's September Precept: When Given the Choice Between Being Right or
  Being Kind, Choose Kind. (16)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (Via) It's not a contest about whose days suck the most, Auggie. The point is
  we all have to put up with the bad days. Now, unless you want to be treated
  like a baby the rest of your life, or like a kid with special needs, you just
  have to suck it up and go. (36)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (Auggie) Funny how sometimes you worry a lot about something and it turns out to be
  nothing. (66)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
  (Mr. Tushman) Always try to be a little kinder than is necessary (92)
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/03/28/wonder/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/03/28/wonder/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Machine Learning Guide</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After AI winter, AI was revived through more realistic applications
(recommenders), better computers, and more data. Also somewhat better algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reactions to AI: fear and optimism. We’ve survived through every revolution so
far&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI is the next stage of evolution. It’s our duty to create AI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ML stages: predict, error, learn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An algorithm is code which describes a machine learning process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gradient descent and linear regression are building blocks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Logistic regression is a bit of a misnomer. Logistic function is performed in
linear regression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A logit is basically a probability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Objective function is the name of the function in the predict step. It is a
sigmoid function in logistic regression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gradient descent is descent to where the error is the lowest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 maths are linear algebra, stats, and calculus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cooking analogy. Linalg is mise en place, stats are the recipe or cookbook,
and calculus is actually cooking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deep learning is closer to &lt;em&gt;automating&lt;/em&gt; a mental task&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deep learning stacks shallow learning algorithms (eg logistic regression
logit)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GPA is a good approximation of PCA&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kernel trick is like looking at a dataset from a different angle so you can
see a better solution. Or like colored goggles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Markov: no current states have dependencies on previous states&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NLP is a good specialization. It’s everywhere.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 levels from lowest to highest: parts, tasks, goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parts are corpora, lexicon, etc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tasks are named entity recognition, part of speech&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goals are text classification, sentiment analysis, spell check&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GPU is 20-100x performance gain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nvidia provides cuda&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pandas to get and munge data. Then pass to numpy for transformations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In CNNs, window and stride gobhand in hand for filter definitions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hyperparameter is anything the human chooses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When feature scaling. Normalization always does 0 to 1. Standardization is
mean 0 with unit stdev. Standardization is more common&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://tigerthinks.com/2019/03/25/machine-learning-guide/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tigerthinks.com/2019/03/25/machine-learning-guide/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
